Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf officially is נ״ב nun
beis 52. We are a bit behind; we're on נ״א nun aleph
at the bottom, where the גמרא Gemara begins right after the משנה.
Mishnah. And the משנה Mishnah has finally laid out, as I've pointed
out to you many a time, that we get to sort of
what you would have expected to be maybe one of the first
משניות mishnayos way in the middle. So now we finally talk about
the base כתובה, Kesuvah, about the 100 and the 200 for a
בתולה. besulah. The משנה Mishnah says that anything less, I'm sorry, 100
for an אלמנה, almanah, 200 for a בתולה, besulah, the משנה Mishnah
says that anything less, or if it was not written in the
כתובה, Kesuvah, it doesn't matter; it's a תנאי בית דין. tnai beis
din. These are obligations that exist because the rabbis imposed them whether
they are written in the כתובה Kesuvah or not. And then it
speaks similarly about the idea of that all of the land is
encumbered, the lien is on all of the property to pay for
the כתובה. Kesuvah. And similarly if the person tried to limit it
and say only a certain field is encumbered, that he does not
have the right; these are requirements of בית דין beis din regardless
of what's written in the כתובה. Kesuvah. And then it goes on
to other issues about the obligation to
redeem
the wife if the wife is taken captive. But the first part
is that even if the person either didn't write or explicitly wrote
otherwise in the כתובה Kesuvah on some of the base obligations, the
100, 200, the שיעבודים, shibudim, it does not, it is not effective.
So now let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara at the
beginning of the wide lines, bottom of נ״א עמוד א׳. nun aleph
amud aleph. מני? Mani? Who is this going like? רבי מאיר היא.
Rabbi Meir hi. It must be Rabbi Meir, דאמר d'amar Rabbi Meir:
כל הפוחת לבתולה ממאתים ולאלמנה ממנה הרי זו בעילת זנות. kol hapoches
libesulah mimasa'im ule'almanah mimana harei zu be'ilas zenus. That anybody who writes
for, you know, a כתובה Kesuvah value less than the standard amount
that the rabbis said, less than 200 for a בתולה besulah or
less than 100 for an אלמנה, almanah, then it is effectively like
the woman is without a כתובה, Kesuvah, and for the husband and
wife to be having sex without a כתובה, Kesuvah, without the protections
of marriage, then it's not like it's even like it's as if
it's like fornication; it's like it's not taking place within the security
and the protections within marriage. So even just anything below the amount
that the rabbis demanded. So that's an important idea that we'll develop
more later, thank you, particularly the idea that, you know, the woman
for her to feel protected, especially in a case where it's unilateral
where the husband can divorce her against her will, if she doesn't
have the protection of the כתובה Kesuvah which makes sure that the
husband won't just callously divorce her, because one of the roles of
the כתובה Kesuvah as we've said is that it prevents the husband
from just callously divorcing his wife; he knows that there's going to
be a cost, so he pauses first. And he knows that if
she's divorced, she's protected. So if she doesn't have those protections and
she knows he can just easily divorce her,
then to her it feels like it's just casual sex; it doesn't
feel like it's done in the marital context with her with the
sense of the protections that that affords and the commitment that that
has. So that's Rabbi Meir's idea that anything less is בעילת זנות.
be'ilas zenus. Now, what does that mean? Does it mean that if
you wrote less in the כתובה, Kesuvah, it automatically is voided and
it goes to the standard amount? Or does it mean if you
wrote less in the כתובה Kesuvah then you're violating, and the continued
married life and having sex together is considered a violation, but that
it does not necessarily, but maybe the actual amount of the כתובה
Kesuvah is what you wrote? Right? Do you understand? There's two different
issues. One is saying that we censure this; it's unacceptable to have
less than 200 and 100; it's unacceptable to be בעילת זנות. be'ilas
zenus. It's another thing to say that if you actually wrote less
than that, that we void what you wrote and we say it's
going to be the standard amount of 200, 100. The גמרא Gemara
assumes that those are the same, and therefore the גמרא Gemara assumes
that the משנה Mishnah works for Rabbi Meir. Since in the end
of the day, Rabbi Meir completely opposes a כתובה Kesuvah less than
200 and 100, therefore we could say that if you wrote less
than 200 and 100, we void that and it's the standard amount.
So our משנה Mishnah is Rabbi Meir, okay. דאי De-ei Rabbi Yehuda,
because if it's Rabbi Yehuda, הא אמר ha amar Rabbi Yehuda: רוצה
כותב לבתולה שטר של מאתים וכותב התקבלתי ממך מנה. rotzeh kosev libesulah
shtar shel masayim vechosev hiskabalti mimech mane.
That if a person can basically write the standard amount, so Rabbi
Yehuda agrees that you need to start with the standard amount, so
you write a כתובה Kesuvah of 200, but then she can write
a document and say, "you already paid off 100," even if he
didn't pay off the 100. Means you could effectively make the amount
100 once you start with a document of 200. Or similarly,
ולאלמנה מנה מנה וכותב התקבלתי ממך חמשים זוז. ule'almanah mana mana vechosev
hiskabalti mimech chamishim zuz.
So you see two things from, so you see from Rabbi Yehuda
that Rabbi Yehuda does not censure the idea of having a כתובה
Kesuvah less than the standard amount. You might have to start with
a standard amount and then you write a receipt in order to
get it to that point, but nevertheless, if bottom line you have
less than the standard amount, he's okay with that. So the משנה
Mishnah assumes that according to Rabbi Yehuda, now you'll obviously notice that
there's a difference here, but the משנה Mishnah will assume if Rabbi
Yehuda says you could start with 200 and write a receipt for
100, then presumably you should also be able to start with 100.
So our משנה Mishnah that doesn't let you start with a lesser
amount, the גמרא Gemara assumes that's only Rabbi Meir. Since in the
end of the day, Rabbi Yehuda allows a כתובה Kesuvah to be
less effectively. Then he should be okay with this משנה Mishnah *Mishna*
if the כתובה Ketubah *Ketubah* was written for less. So therefore it
assumes that our משנה Mishnah *Mishna* is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir*. All right, that's point number one. אימא סיפא Seifa *Eima seifa*,
let's look at the end of the משנה Mishna *Mishna*. כתב לה
שדה שוה מנה תחת מאתים זוז zuz *Katav la sadeh shaveh maneh
tachas maasayim zuz*, if the guy wrote that this field worth 100
is what has the שעבודים *shibbudim*, it has the liens on it
for the 200 זוז zuz *zuz* of the כתובה Ketubah, *Ketubah*, ולא
כתב לה *v'lo katav la*, and he didn't write the standard language
of the כתובה Ketubah *Ketubah*, which is in our כתובה Ketubah *Ketubah*,
כל נכסין דאית לי אחראין לכתובתיך *kol nichasin d'is li achrayin l'chtubaseich*,
all of my property is encumbered for the כתובה Ketubah *Ketubah*, so
חייב chayav, *chayav*, nevertheless he's obligated, the lien applies to all the
property, תנאי בית דין tnai Beit Din. *t'nai beis din*, because that
is mandated by the בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din*. Okay. So
אתיא לרבי יהודה *atya l'Rabbi Yehuda*, one minute, that doesn't work. We
just said the beginning of the משנה Mishna *Mishna* that says it
can't be less than 200 or 100 is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir,
*Rabbi Meir*. Because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah. *Rabbi Yehuda* allows it to
be effectively less than 200 and 100. This idea that if you
wrote a lesser lien we ignore that, that sounds like that's going
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah *Rabbi Yehuda*. Why? What רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*? דאמר אחריות טעות סופר achrayut ta'ut sofer, הוא *D'amar
achrayus ta'os sofer hu*, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* says
the lack of writing liens in a document is considered to be
a mistake of the scribe, which is a funny way of saying
that basically we assume that any loan that you have a document
for automatically has liens accompanying it. Whether it's written in the document
that there will be liens on the property or not, the fact
that you have a written loan automatically includes the liens. So the
way we say that is, if the liens were not written in
the document itself, well, that was just a mistake of the scribe.
It doesn't mean anything. All right. So therefore the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying if you wrote, now here clearly you can't be talking
about a mistake of the scribe because the scribe explicitly wrote the
only lien for this כתובה Ketubah *Ketubah* is on this one field
of 100. So nobody's making any mistakes, nobody forgot to write something.
But nevertheless, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*'s point is, once you
have a loan in a document,
the liens automatically result from that document. So therefore this משנה Mishna
*Mishna* that says that even if you wrote the liens only on
one field they apply on everything, that follows רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* that says a שטר Shtar. *shtar* comes automatically with liens
whether they're written or not, or even if something specifically otherwise is
written in the שטר *shtar*. That says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*. דבי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*De'Rabbi Meir*, because if it was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir*,
האמר אחריות achrayus לאו טעות taut. סופר הוא *ha'amar achrayus lav ta'os
sofer hu*, he says if you didn't write the liens in the
document it's not a mistake and it would be a loan without
liens. דתנן *Detnan*, we taught in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. מוצא שטר
חוב *Motzei shtar chov*, if somebody finds a document, a loan document
on
the street. Okay, it says that ראובן Reuven *Reuven* borrowed 100 dollars
from שמעון Shimon *Shimon*. And now you go ahead and first of
all so you don't know who dropped this document. Did ראובן Reuven
*Reuven* borrow it after he had paid שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* back and
now it was already a paid up debt? Or did שמעון Shimon.
*Shimon* drop it and ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* still owed him the money?
So obviously you would not go ahead and give it back to
שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* because maybe the debt had been paid. But you
go over to ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* and you say ראובן Reuven. *Reuven*,
what's the story with this document? I found it. He says oh,
that's שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s, I haven't paid up the debt yet. So
maybe then you would assume שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s document, ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
agrees, you go ahead and you return it to שמעון Shimon *Shimon*.
Nevertheless the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* teaches אם יש בהם אחריות נכסים im
yesh bahem achrayut nechasim, לא יחזיר lo yachzir, *im yesh bahem achrayus
nechasim lo yachzir*. If there are liens that are included in this
document you can't give it to שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, שבית דין יפרעו
מהן *she'beis din yifre'u meihen*, because then בית דין Beis Din *Beis
Din* would exact the liens. What does that mean? It means we're
afraid of the following. We're afraid that ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* have decided to use this opportunity as a little bit
of a scheme. And therefore what they're saying is like the following.
Actually ראובן Reuven *Reuven* has paid up the loan. Okay? So he
doesn't owe שמעון Shimon *Shimon* anything. But what's going to happen now,
you'll return this document to שמעון *Shimon*, שמעון *Shimon* will come to
ראובן Reuven *Reuven* to pay up the loan again, they have now
a scheme going between them. And ראובן Reuven *Reuven* would say oh
I'm sorry I don't have any money. So שמעון *Shimon* would now
go and seize the property that has the liens on it from
people that bought it off of ראובן Reuven's *Reuven*, and then they'll
split it between them. Okay? So we're afraid of that and therefore
you don't return the document. Now of course if we were genuinely
afraid of that all the time then we would say every time
ראובן Reuven. *Reuven* pays up a loan you have to tear up
the document. You can't give it back to ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* because
maybe they'll just reuse it, right? So as a general rule we're
not afraid. This is an interesting idea that comes up in בבא
מציעא *Bava Metzia*, that if we find the document lying in the
street that makes us feel like that makes us suspicious. Because we
basically feel that שמעון *Shimon* would never have been so careless with
the document. Like this is 100 dollars. He wouldn't have been so
careless with it. So if it's lying in the street it probably
fell from ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. Because it probably was already paid and
therefore ראובן Reuven *Reuven* was more careless. And that makes us suspicious
and therefore we won't give it back even if ראובן Reuven. *Reuven*
says that it's שמעון *Shimon*'s. Okay? Generally we're not concerned about this,
but you find a lost document, it doesn't have as much sort
of like weight because it's lying in the middle of the street
and therefore you can't just give it back to שמעון *Shimon*.
Yeah you would note on paid and all kind of thing or
on any of these things.
Yeah you would assume even if you gave it to ראובן Reuven
*Reuven* you would write paid on it. So maybe that's also that's
true. Look from a הלכה halacha *halakhic* perspective or from a לומדות
*lamdus* perspective the way of saying this is that a שטר *shtar*
is not considered to be. to be made to testify unless it's
being held by the person who is the bearer of the document.
And if שמעון is holding the document, it's testifying that ראובן Reuven
owes him the money. If you find it on the street, it's
not testifying to anything. So to take a piece of paper and
give it to שמעון and turn it into testimony is something that
requires a good amount of proof before you're prepared to do that.
Okay, so אם יש בהם אחריות achrayus נכסים, לא יחזיר, yachzir, don't
give it back שבית דין נפרעין מהן. shebeit din nifra'in mehen. אם
אין בהם אחריות נכסים, im ein bahem achrayut nechasim, if there are
no liens written in the document, יחזיר, then give it back to
שמעון, שאין בית דין נפרעין מהן she'ein beit din nifra'in mehen because
then there would be no way that any third party can be
implicated that you can seize the property that was sold to a
third party. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir said, meaning if there are no liens written in the
document, then it doesn't have liens. Then you can't, then you know,
we don't say that anything that's a written document automatically has liens.
If there are no liens written in it, then there are no
liens. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, but the sages say, אחד זה ואחד
זה לא יחזיר, echad zeh ve'echad zeh lo yachzir, either way don't
return it שבית דין נפרעין מהן shebeit din nifra'in mehen because the
בית דין will always go ahead and exact the, and you know,
and exercise liens on a written שטר. So this is the idea
that anytime you have a loan written in a document, it automatically
entails the liens that come with it. The שיבודים Shibudim come automatically
with it, and the way the גמרא Gemara phrases that is אחריות
achrayus. טעות taut. סופר, we assume it's a mistake of the scribe.
But we don't really mean the mistake of the scribe because we
might know the scribe, like in this case explicitly said, you know,
liens are only on this field, etc., and we're still going to
say
that the liens are on everything. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that
therefore what do we have? רישא Reisha רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the
beginning of the משנה Mishnah that says the כתובה Kesuba can't be
less than two hundred or a hundred is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir.
that says anything less is בעילת זנות. be'ilat zenut. סיפא רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda And the end of it that says that if you
had tried to make the שיבודים Shibudim less than they normally are,
that there's still the full שיבודים, Shibudim, that's like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that says that any document automatically has שיבודים. Shibudim. So the
גמרא Gemara says, how do you make sense of it? וכי תימא,
vechi teima,
so there are going to be some obvious answers which the גמרא
Gemara will say, וכי תימא כולה רבי מאיר היא, vechi teima kullah
Rabbi Meir hi, maybe it's all רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, ושאני ליה
לרבי מאיר בין כתובה לשטרי, veshani leh leRabbi Meir bein Ketubah leShtarei,
maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes a distinction. He says by a
normal document I'll assume there are no liens if there's not written
in. By a כתובה, Kesuba maybe כתובה Kesuba. special. By כתובה Kesuba,
we say that's what the משנה Mishnah means when it says תנאי
בית דין. So the כתובה Kesuba. I'll assume there always are liens.
Okay, a normal document not, but a כתובה Kesuba yes. Though ומי
שאני ליה? umi shani leh? He really doesn't make this distinction. והתניא,
vehatanya, do we teach a ברייתא, Baraita, חמישה גובין מן המחוחררין? hamisha
govin min hamachurarin?
Five things you can only collect from those unencumbered property. Right, שחרור
Shichrur like בני חורין, Bnei Chorin, it's about to be פסח, Pesach,
מחוחררין machurarin means the free property as opposed to the משועבדים, meshubadim,
שיבוד, Shibud, עבודה, Avodah,
right, didn't know there's going to be a פסח Pesach theme here,
okay.
So anyway, so מחוחררין machurarin is your property that's בני חורין, Bnei
Chorin, they're not encumbered, they're free, meaning that they're in your control,
you haven't sold them to a third party. So there are five
things that do not have liens, that you could only collect from
the property that is being held by the person who owes you
the money, not by property that actually he has sold to somebody
else. What are these five things? ואלו הן, ve'elu hen, these are
they: פירות ושבח פירות, peirot veshevach peirot, fruit and the benefit of
fruit, which means the following. It's a case fact that
somebody
steals a field and sells it, ראובן steals a field and sells
it to שמעון. Okay. Then comes along לוי, Levi, the owner of
the field, and manages to prove it's his and takes it back
from שמעון. All right. Now שמעון goes back to ראובן, whatever the
court did to ראובן, שמעון still wants his money back from ראובן.
שמעון goes back to ראובן to get his money back for paying
for the field. Okay, ראובן doesn't have any money, so שמעון collects
the money that ראובן owed him, right, you get this, שמעון paid
ראובן for the field that wound up to be stolen, anyway, שמעון
now goes ahead and gets his money back from people that ראובן
sold ראובן fields to. Is this confusing or you got this? Should
I draw this?
Okay, we'll call them גנב. Ganav. Okay, we'll call them owner,
גנב, Ganav, and buyer. Okay, so this one field was owned by
this guy, stolen by him, sold to him. Okay, then the owner
comes and he realizes it's his field and he gets his field
back. All right. The buyer now says, give me my money. Okay,
he wants to be paid back. Pay me back for the field
that you stole that I bought from you. Okay, the גנב Ganav
doesn't have any money to pay him back. Okay, but the גנב
Ganav has sold his, the גנב Ganav's fields to these other people.
This will be ראובן. The גנב Ganav sold his field to ראובן,
one that he really did own.
So he wants his money back, so he can't get it from
the גנב, Ganav, but he... get it from the people that the
גנב ganav sold the field for because when the גנב ganav sold
the field here, that put liens on these, on this property that
he had owned at that time, that if, that if he ever
had to reimburse the guy, the guy would be able to get
them his money back from the property that the גנב ganav had.
Okay, so he's going to now go to the fields that were
in the גנב's ganav control when he bought it and therefore he
has liens and now they're under ראובן's control and he's going to
go get his money back. Okay, the only thing is the following:
while the field was in the buyer's control, he was going ahead
and he planted it and he, and he, you know, and he
plowed it and there's now grain growing and all the whole thing.
And then when the owner took it back, he took it back
with a nice improved field, a field that's been plowed and fertilized
and with all this grain. So the buyer has invested that money
in that field. He's entitled to that money back because the whole
thing was the גנב's ganav fault. He's entitled to get reimbursed for
that investment from the גנב. ganav. Okay, he can not go ahead,
he can only get it from property that is in the גנב's
ganav direct control. He cannot get it from ראובן because since that
amount is unfixed, right? It could be twenty years he's been investing
money in the field or whatever it is. Since that's a non-fixed
amount, it's not fair to ראובן. When ראובן bought it from this
guy, he knows there's somebody out there who has a lien on
this field that I might, that might seize it. But that was
a fixed amount, right? It would not be fair for ראובן to
buy this and have an indefinite amount that might be, that might
be, that might be indebted. So that's the basic rule here. You
can't have a lien according to this משנה Mishnah on, on amounts
that are, that are like unspecified, indefinite, you know, that might be,
that might be ongoing debts. Did you have a question, דוב? Dov?
I'm just trying to figure this out. So the lien is only
on the original amount that he paid for the field? Right, exactly.
If the real estate itself subsequently became more
valued, right, that he can't collect for because that wasn't his outlay.
But the money he invested in it was his outlay.
Are there limitations on how long that buyer can get the field
back, the גנב's ganav field back? In other words, the property? Are
there any time limits on this?
No, not if it's for the base amount. But for the, but
we do limit the, you know, that it can't be an ongoing,
like amount, an increasing amount, right. But no, but there's no time
limit. Okay, so פירות ושבח פירות והמקבל עליו לזון את בן אשתו
ואת בת אשתו. Peiros v'shevach peiros v'hamikabel alav lazon es ben ishto
v'es bas ishto. Somebody who obligates himself, let's say as a כתובה
Kesuba obligation, that he will, whatever he obligates himself, to pay his
stepchildren, his stepson or his stepdaughter. Because again, מזונות mezonos is an
indefinite ongoing obligation. So if he then goes ahead and dies and
the, or whatever, or he sold his field, let's say he didn't
die, you cannot go ahead and get paid those things off from
fields that are sold because that is a non-fixed amount, that's an
ongoing amount. You might, by the way, remember the דף daf we
just did yesterday about the daughters being supported from the קרקע. karka.
That if that land of the estates switches hands, it's not so
clear that the daughters can continue to be supported from it because
again, it's an ongoing indefinite amount. Okay, so this can only be
collected from property that is in the person's direct control.
And finally, this is וכתובת אשה שאין בה אחריות. u'kesuvas isha she'ein
bo achrayus. I'm sorry, וגט חוב שאין בו אחריות, v'get chov she'ein
bo achrayus, excuse me,
a normal loan document without, without liens written in it. וכתובת אשה
שאין בה אחריות, u'kesuvas isha she'ein bo achrayus, a כתובה Kesuba without
liens written in it. So you see explicitly that if there are
not liens written in it, you don't assume liens. מאן תנא דאמר
אחריות לאו טעות סופר? Man tana d'amar achrayus lav taus sofer? Who
is he? Who is the one that says that lack of writing
liens is not considered a mistake? We assume that it means what
it says. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir And
that's why this ברייתא braisa that we just quoted is רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir. and that's why it says that in a normal document
without liens, there are no liens. דקתני, d'katni, and it says that
the same is true by a כתובה. Kesuba. וכתובת אשה. Kesuvas isha.
So now we have, here, so it's clear that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir, says that if you don't write liens in a כתובה, Kesubah,
there are no liens. By the way, it's pretty interesting. You would
have thought that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who is so מקפיד makpid
that you don't go below the 200 and 100 would also insist
on the full normal demands of בית דין of there being liens
on the כתובה. Kesubah But maybe again, maybe there he's having to,
he feels he needs to protect the purchasers, you know, not just
the husband and wife. There are other people that are involved there.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says while it can't be less than
200 and 100, it can exist without liens. ורבי יהודה v'Rabbi Yehuda
seems to say the flip: it can be less than 200 and
100, but the liens are full. So who is our משנה Mishnah
going like? Our משנה Mishnah saying it has to be the full
200, 100 and there have to be the full liens. So the
גמרא Gemara, says אי בעית אימא רבי מאיר ואי בעית אימא רבי
יהודה. I bayis eima Rabbi Meir v'i bayis eima Rabbi Yehuda. You
can make it work either way. אי בעית אימא רבי יהודה, התם
כתב לה התקבלתי, הכא לא כתב לה התקבלתי.
I bayis eima Rabbi Yehuda, hasam kasav lah hiskabalti, hacha lo
kasav lah hiskabalti. This was the most obvious answer. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, made a very funny statement. He said you could write a
כתובה Kesubah of 200 and get a receipt of 100. Why didn't
he just say the easier thing: you could write a כתובה Kesubah
of 100? So it's clear that according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda
you have to start with the base כתובה Kesubah, that the rabbis
instituted. You have to write the base כתובה. Kesubah, than 200. Less
is not acceptable. After you've written that כתובה, Kesubah if he wants
to go ahead and waive 100 or give or write a receipt,
that's up to you, you can live with the כתובה Kesubah obligation
as less than 200, but the base כתובה Kesubah. has to be
written with that 200. Okay, so one way of explaining the משנה
Mishnah is, the משנה Mishnah says you can't have a כתובה Kesubah,
less than 200 and 100. Who's that going like? Maybe it's רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Although רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that you can,
you can write a receipt and make it effectively less, you can't
start it off as less than 200 and 100. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'is
eima, if you want you could say רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir מאי
חייב דקתני מינה משעבדי Mai chayav de'kasani mina meshu'abadi or could even
be רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir but when the משנה Mishnah. says that
if you wrote that you only have a lien on one field,
that you still have a full lien on the כתובה, Kesubah it
doesn't mean that you have a full lien on all the real
estate, it means you only have a lien on the unencumbered property.
I have a feeling that I am losing everybody right now.
Wait, can I one, can I ask you a question? Yes.
Who stands to be paid back for the שבח פירות shvach peiros
of that originally stolen field? What's the investment, who invested?
The purchaser, the buyer.
But if the field was stolen, he, in other words, how is
it that it was under his control? If it was stolen from
me, he spent all those years trying to prove title that it
was really his field and not the גנב. ganav.
Maybe the גנב ganav had forged a document and then it was
eventually proved, and it looked like it was the גנב's ganav and
then eventually was proven in court that it never was the גנב's.
ganav
But in the meantime all those years the original buyer had been...
Exactly, exactly.
And he had built a house and he had done whatever, and
he had spent a hundred thousand dollars in improvement.
And then the גנב ganav comes along and says this is really
my field.
No, the court, the owner comes along and says, the court comes
along and says you bought it from a גנב ganav and the
owner is taking it back. And now he wants his reimbursement from
the גנב. ganav.
He acted in good faith from the גנב. ganav. He bought it
from the
גנב.
ganav. Ah, got it, right, right, right. The whole thing was a
scam from
לכתחילה. lechatchila.
Okay,
so I have a feeling I'm losing people. So here, let me
do this again. Okay, so here you have the...
Okay. So, so, okay, one minute.
These are the two debates,
okay, these are the two debates of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. and
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Okay, by כתובה, Kesubah? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you can have a כתובה Kesubah less than 200 and less
than 100, although the case he gives is that you wrote a
receipt so you effectively made it less, but it's, but at the
end of the day, it's less. Whereas רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
a כתובה Kesuvah always has to be the full amount. In general
by other documents, רבי יהודה says that you always assume אחריות if
it's written, whereas רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, says you only assume אחריות
is only present if it's explicitly written in, and we see he
says that even by a כתובה. Kesuvah Okay, our problem is that
our משנה Mishnah said that when it comes to a כתובה, Kesuvah
what did our משנה Mishnah say? Our משנה Mishnah said that a
כתובה ksuva is always 200 or 100 depending on אלמנה בתולה almana
besula and always
אחריות. Right? Always. So who's it going like? Right? Can't be going
like either.
Do they not like the fact that it's כתובה?
ksuva So the easiest answer is that it's רבי יהודה, that רבי
יהודה says yes, effectively it can be less than 200 and 100,
but you gotta start it at the base amount. If you want
to write a receipt afterwards, געזונטערהייט, gezunterheit, you're allowed to, you're allowed
to effectively make it less but the base amount has to start
with what amount that the Rabbis said. So that's the easy answer
that our משנה Mishnah is רבי יהודה. The other answer is our
משנה Mishna is רבי מאיר and when the משנה says that if
you wrote that you only have rights to liens on a particular
field you're still חייב, chayav it didn't mean that you have liens
on the whole property. It actually means you only have liens on
that field. But what it means is you're still חייב the full
amount from the property that you have that's under your control, but
property that you sold actually you would not have the, you would
not have those liens and that would be if it were following
רבי מאיר. But that's not the simple sense of the משנה. The
simple sense of the משנה is, is that you cannot limit the
liens, the liens are going to be full because that's what the
Rabbis demand and therefore it makes sense that our משנה is רבי
יהודה and that רבי יהודה is saying you have to start with
this base amount even if afterwards you could effectively make it less.
What if the field is not worth 200 זוז and he owes
200 זוז to his divorcee? Right, then he's still responsible for the
other 100.
The question is is he responsible and then are there liens on
the other property for the other 100 or is he just personally
responsible? So רבי מאיר would say that he's just personally responsible whereas
רבי יהודה would say and that's the simple sense of the משנה
is that there are liens on the, on the rest of the
property for the other 100. Okay, so now we move on. So
that was about the base amount of the כתובה ksuva and about
that these obligations exist even without the document. All right, now we
move on. לא כתב לה. Lo kasav lah. Oh my God, we're
falling more and more behind. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. So now we deal with the issue about,
now we get to a, the issue about the מצוה mitzvah to
redeem. man to redeem the מצוה, mitzvah, the כתובה ksuva obligation for
a man to redeem his wife, but also the implicit difference in
the משנה that if she's married to a ישראל, Yisroel, then he'll
redeem her and we are going to assume that if she was
taken captive,
she was or might have been raped. If she's married to ישראל,
Yisroel, he'll redeem her and therefore he will, what do you call
it, continue to be married to her. If she's married to a
כהן, Kohen, he'll redeem her but then he'll have to divorce her
because even for a wife of a כהן, Kohen, even if she's
raped, she's not allowed to continue to live with her husband. So
let's take a look now what the גמרא Gemara said about that
before it gets to the כתובה ksuva obligations. It's going to deal
with this difference about the consequences of rape between a wife of
a ישראל Yisroel and a wife of a כהן. Kohen. So let's
take a look. אמר אבוה דשמואל, Amar Avuhu deShmuel, the father of
שמואל Shmuel said: אשת ישראל שנאנסה, Eishes Yisroel shena'ansa, the wife of
a non-כהן Kohen who was raped, אסורה לבעלה, asura leba'ala, she's forbidden
to her husband. חיישינן, Chayshinan, why? שמא תחלתה באונס וסופה ברצון. Shema
techilasa be'ones vesofa beratzon. This is a very, very difficult גמרא, Gemara.
again, you know, you can't imagine that this would have been that
you know that this could ever be written from a female perspective.
But you know the גמרא Gemara is saying that we're afraid that
even though she's being raped, somewhere in the middle of being raped,
she actually decides that she actually wants to have sex with this
guy. Okay, very difficult idea in the גמרא. Gemara. Now what the
גמרא Gemara will discuss later on is that a woman might who
is being held captive and under threat for life, and we've seen
this before, might agree willingly to have sex because she's doing that
in terms in big picture in terms of trying to protect her
life, right? So the act itself might be willing, but ultimately it's
because she's afraid, you know, she's doing what she has to do
to stay alive. As opposed to this, this does not sound like
that at all. This sounds like he actually has already begun raping
her and having intercourse with her, and in the middle, she's deciding
that she actually wants it. Okay, very difficult גמרא. Gemara Yes, Charlie?
What about how she
was, yeah, she became, right,
she
became interested to stay with that person, you know?
So I don't know if this is... Oh, you're saying maybe it's
not during the same act.
Maybe it's like over time, psychology of
identifying with your captors, you know?
It's interesting. So you're sort of, same idea, yeah, okay, that's an
interesting point. But what you mean is it's not during the same
act, similar to what I was saying before but not in the
same way, meaning we're talking over a period of time that eventually
it becomes ברצון. beratzon. Out, right. Now the ברצון beratzon of, it's
an interesting point because the ברצון beratzon of, I'm doing what I
have to do to stay alive even though I don't want to
do it, is basically considered אונס. ones. Actually there's a whole discussion
of רש"י ותוספות Rashi Tosafos before, but if somebody's afraid for their
life and they're basically agreeing, you know, willingly having sex with their
captors or doing whatever they're doing, but ultimately it's because they, you
know, they feel they have to do this to stay alive, that
very well, you know, might be considered אונס ones ultimately, you know.
But your example is an interesting one. Your example is that eventually
you actually sort of, you know, your whole mindset shifts about this
and you become identified with your captors. It's interesting. I think we'll
see a later גמרא Gemara that it talks about like even in
mid-act, you know, and that's I think the normal assumption we're talking
about mid-act, but the way you're framing it at least makes it
possible to imagine what the גמרא Gemara is talking about. Yes, Charlie.
All right, so let's take a look. Okay, so he says therefore
even if it's a case of being captive, she's forbidden to the
wife of a ישראל. Yisroel. איתיביה
רב לאבוה דשמואל, Eisivei Rav la'Avuhu deShmuel, so רב Rav asked the
father of שמואל, Shmuel, אם תשתבאי, Im tishatvai, the language of the
כתובה ksuva is, if you're taken captive, אפרקינך, afarkinach, I will redeem
you, ואותבינך לי לאינתו, ve'osvinach li le'intu, and I'll take you back
as my wife. So you see that a woman who returns to
the, the wife of a ישראל Yisroel after being held captive is
allowed to go back to her husband. אישתיק, Ishtik, he was silent.
He didn't have an answer. So, קרי רב עליה דאבוה דשמואל, Kari
Rav alei deAvuhu deShmuel, so רב Rav then said regarding, referring to
the father of שמואל, Shmuel, רב Rav was the one who asked
the question, שרים עצרו במלים, Sarim atzru bemilim, that the, you know,
great people were held back with their words, וכף ישימו לפיהם, vechaf
yasimu lefihem, and they'll put a, you know, they'll put their hands
to their mouths. So meaning like he, you know, he was silent
but he didn't have to be silent. מאי הוה ליה למימר, Mai
hava lei lemeimar, he could have had a response. The response could
have been בשבויה הקילו. Bishvuya heikilu. Our case is a case where
the woman is taken captive. If she's taken captive, we don't know
that she was raped, right? What the father of שמואל Shmuel said
is a woman who was raped, we know she was raped. Okay,
if we know she was raped, then we're afraid that maybe she
did in the end she wanted to do it willingly. Whereas if
she's taken captive, maybe she was never raped. So since it's possible
she was never raped, we allow her to go back to her
husband. But if we know she was raped, we're afraid that she
in the end did it willingly. And that, by the way, David,
is why I think, although I would like your explanation to be
correct, you know,
the statement of the father of שמואל Shmuel is not specifically a
statement of being taken captive, it's just a statement about a woman
who is raped. Some guy jumps on a woman in
the... The context was what exactly the
husband wrote in the
משנה as being kept.
Right, and that's what the גמרא Gemara says that that's...
yes, but the
גמרא Gemara says that that שמואל Shmuel would agree she can go
back because maybe she wasn't raped. When שמואל Shmuel said she's forbidden
to her husband, it wasn't a case of being taken captive. It
was just a case of us directly witnessing her being raped. So
that's why I think that the גמרא Gemara is while I appreciate
your explanation, the whole point of גמרא Gemara here is that שמואל
Shmuel was talking about a straight case of rape, which makes it
on the one hand more of a problem because we know that
she had sex with this guy. On the other hand, you and
I and I think everybody would all think that how can you
imagine that she was willing in the middle of an act of
rape? So now and you'll see in a minute that the גמרא
Gemara assumes that שמואל's Shmuel position is the father of שמואל's Shmuel
position is by all things, not just by. Let's take a look
at the next line. ולאבוה דשמואל, Ule'avuha de'Shmuel,
according to the father of שמואל, Shmuel, אונס דשרי רחמנא היכי משכחת
לה? ones desharei Rachmana heichi mashkachat lah?
When the תורה Torah says by the סוטה, Sotah, a woman who's
suspected of committing adultery, it says והיא לא נתפשה, vehi lo nitpasha,
that she wasn't
raped. So meaning the תורה Torah implies that if a woman was
raped, she's allowed to go back to her husband. So how does
שמואל Shmuel make... the father of שמואל Shmuel make sense of this?
The father of שמואל Shmuel says that even if a woman's raped,
she's not allowed to go back to her husband, but it's implicit
in the תורה Torah that she is.
So אונס
דשרי רחמנא היכי משכחת לה?
ones desharei Rachmana
heichi mashkachat lah? כגון דקאמרי עדים, kegon dekamrei edim, and here you
see explicitly, David, against what you were suggesting, I keep on going
back now because I would have liked to have said what you
said, but כגון דקאמרי עדים, kegon dekamrei edim, the only case a
woman can go back to her husband after being raped is that
the witnesses say שצווחה מתחילה ועד סוף. shetzavcha mitechila ve'ad sof. She
was yelling and screaming from the very beginning of the act to
the end. But if somewhere in the middle she stopped screaming and
protesting, then we're assuming that she in the end is a willing
participant. Again, it's just horrific to imagine this.
Instead of helping her, they are watching as witnesses.
Well, okay. That's also true, but who knows what the circumstances are.
I wouldn't focus on the witnesses at this point. ופליגא דרבא. U'pliga
de'Rava. This argues on רבא. Rava. דאמר רבא, De'amar Rava, now, because
רבא Rava says כל שתחילתה באונס וסופה ברצון, kol shetechilata be'ones vesofa
beratzon, if it began as force even if in the end it
was willing, so again, he's not disagreeing with his understanding of the
facts that it's possible that it's willing in the end, אפילו היא
אומרת הניחו לו, afilu hi omeret hanichu lo, even were she to
say, 'Don't do anything, don't stop him,' שאילמלא נזקק לה היא שוכרתו,
she'ilmale nizkak lah hi socharto, that even had he not forced himself
upon me, I would have even paid him to have sex with
me. Okay, so she actually explicitly says this. All right, even in
such a case, מותרת, mutteret, she's permissible. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? יצר
אלבשה, yeitzer albasha, her יצר הרע yeitzer hara got the better of
her. Okay, so since she was forced at the beginning of the
process and that was against her will, even if now it somehow
elicits sexual desire, again, very hard to imagine any of this, and
even if it elicits desire to the point that she says I
wanted to have sex with him even from beforehand, all of that
we think is resulting from the fact that it all began from
a rape and from an אונס, ones, and therefore no expression of
רצון ratzon should be considered as רצון. ratzon. Okay, so this is
a very important halachic principle of תחילתה בפשיעה וסופה באונס... techilata befoshia
vesofa be'ones... well, actually no, that's a different principle, but it's actually
related. Okay, this is תחילתה באונס וסופה ברצון. techilata be'ones vesofa beratzon.
It's all defined by the original אונס. ones. There's a different principle,
for example, by negligence issues of תחילתה בפשיעה וסופה באונס, techilata befoshia
vesofa be'ones, which is let's say I'm negligent with your object, but
then some accident occurs to it. Maybe it doesn't matter, maybe because
of the initial negligence everything that happens afterwards is defined as a
result of the negligence. So this is... that's by sort of דיני
dinei torts. This is by this issue, which is any sense of
desire that comes afterwards might be rooted in the original אונס. ones.
Now that might help explain your Patty Hearst case. So if you
imagine a case which is not... which is, yes, she's been held
captive all this time, I mean, I think that's an interesting question
about how responsible do you see her for her later actions if
it resulted from this captivity? So that's what רבא Rava is saying,
that even if the person is willing and expresses complete willingness, we
all see this rooted in that original אונס. ones. Although again, רבא's
Rava case is that it's all one act. I'm not sure what
he would say about a long-term thing over long-term process. All right,
so what you have here is really fascinating issues of defining אונס
ones and
רצון, ratzon, and it starts as I said pretty horrifically by imagining
that this woman who's being raped in the middle might... certainly אבוה
דשמואל avuha de'Shmuel who says even with her just being quiet and
not protesting, we're going to see that not as just not trying
to make...
normally you would say why is she not protesting anymore? Because it's
not doing any good and it's just making things more difficult for
her and it doesn't mean at all that she wants it or
whatever. The first hard point is that אבוה דשמואל Avo d'Shmuel is
going to interpret her silence as if she wants it. Right, that's
very hard to even begin to imagine and then he says and
therefore it's a problem, it's רצון. ratzon. And רבא Rava goes to
the opposite extreme. He doesn't, maybe in that case of שמואל Shmuel
maybe he would say he wouldn't interpret the facts the way אבוה
דשמואל Avo d'Shmuel did. But even if it's explicit and she says
I want to be having sex with this guy, we don't believe,
you know, we believe that that all resulted from, was initiated by
the original אונס ones and therefore cannot really be defined as רצון.
ratzon. So that's רבא's Rava's position.
Okay, מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? תניא כוותיה דרבא. Tanya k'vatei d'Rava. We
taught like רבא. Rava. והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. V'hi lo nitpasha asura.
It says again if she was not taken, if she was not
seized, she's forbidden to her husband if she slept with another man.
הנתפשה מותרת. Hanitpasha muteret. If she was raped then she's permitted to
go back to her husband. ויש לך אחרת V'yesh lach acheret and
there's another woman שאף על פי שלא נתפשה מותרת sh'af al pi
shelo nitpasha muteret even if she was not raped she's permissible to
her husband. ואיזו היא V'eizo hi which is this? ואיזו זו? V'eizo
zo? כל שתחילתה באונס וסופה
ברצון. Kol shetchilata b'ones v'sofa b'ratzon. If it began by a force,
even if in the end it was willing, then we would say
that she can go back to her husband. And yeah, I think
it is an interesting question, what if it's even over a longer
period of time like this case of, you know, that David was
discussing. Maybe that also would be considered אונס. ones. תניא אידך Tanya
idach we taught another ברייתא. braita. והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. V'hi lo
nitpasha asura. הנתפשה מותרת. Hanitpasha muteret. She was not raped she's forbidden,
if she was raped she's permissible. ויש לך אחרת שאף על פי
שנתפשה אסורה V'yesh lach acheret sh'af al pi she'nitpasha asura and there's
another woman even though she wasn't raped she's forbidden to go back
to her husband. I'm sorry even though, excuse me, even though she
was raped she's forbidden to go back to her husband. ואיזו זו
V'eizo zo what is this? אשת כהן eshet kohen ואיזו זו אשת
כהן. V'eizo zo eshet kohen. This is the wife of a כהן
kohen that even a wife of a כהן kohen who's raped is
forbidden to go back to her husband. That's the second part of
the ברייתא. braita. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי ישמעאל. Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Yishmael. והיא לא נתפשה V'hi lo
nitpasha אסורה. asura. If she was not raped she's forbidden. הנתפשה מותרת.
Hanitpasha muteret. If she was raped she's permitted. ויש לך אחרת שאף
על פי שלא נתפשה מותרת V'yesh lach acheret sh'af al pi shelo
nitpasha muteret and there's another woman that even though she was not
raped and even if she committed adultery she's permitted to go back
to her husband. What would be this woman? ואיזו זו שקדושיה קדושי
טעות. V'eizo zo she'kidusheiha kidushei taut. This is that the original marriage
was a טעות. taut שאפילו בנה מורכב על כתפה Sh'afillu bna murkav
al kteifa even if her כתפה, kteifa, even if her child is
on her shoulder, ממאנת והולכת לה. memaenet v'holechet la.
She can refuse, you know, her original husband and go free. Which
means basically it's a woman married a guy and she's been living
with him for ten years, and somehow you discover ten years later
that the whole thing was a טעות. I don't know what a
טעות was. She thought, you know, he had lied to her about
some essential thing. I mean, whatever, this happens actually, you want a
contemporary example of it, it's he turns out that he was gay,
okay? And that he knew he was gay at the time that
they got married and he was hiding the fact and so on.
So you know, I mean, whatever,
it's discussed in contemporary פוסקים. poskim. But logically of course that should
be, you know, the, you know, it should of course be defined
as a קדושי טעות. kidushei taut. You shouldn't logically you shouldn't even
need a גט. get. Of course it was a mistake. Had you
known those facts that were being, you know, hidden from the person,
then they never would have gotten married. But they were married for
ten years and they had a kid or whatever, and then in
the course of it she went ahead and she committed adultery, okay?
So the הלכה is she's not forbidden, like she didn't commit adultery,
I mean she wouldn't be forbidden to her husband if she wanted
to have sex with him again, she wouldn't be forbidden to the
man she had sex with because in the end it was a
קדושי טעות kidushei taut and even if there's a child, it's still
the original wedding could be null and void even if they've been
living together for ten years and even if there are kids. Okay,
so there is a scenario where a woman could commit adultery and
not be forbidden if it turned out that the original marriage was
קדושי טעות. kidushei taut. Okay. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. הני
נשי דגנבי גנבי Hanni nashei d'ganvi ganvei שריין לגברייהו. sharyon l'gavraihu.
Women that are stolen by, taken captive by just like bandits can
go back to their husbands. Because they're if they were raped, it
was they wouldn't have done it willingly and therefore they can go
back to their husbands. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב יהודה Amru lei rabanan
l'Rav Yehuda so the rabbis said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, והא
קא ממתיין להו נהמא. v'ha ka mamatyan lehu nahama. What do you
mean? They seem like willing participants after they've been held like, you
know, in the with Robin Hood and his merry men there in
the woods for a long time. They start to participate, they bring
them bread for their meals. So, מחמת יראה. machmat yira. That's just
because they're afraid that if they don't participate what's going to happen
to them. והא קא משלחין להו גירי V'ha ka mashl'chin lehu giri
but they sort of hand them their arrows during when they're fighting
in war, you know, everything it seems like they're very willing participants.
No, מחמת יראה. machmat yira. That's all out of fear. Okay. ודאי
שבקינהו ואזלו מנפשייהו אסירן. Vadai shavkinhu v'azlu minafshaihu asiran. If
there's no question that if the captors would say you're free to
go and they chose to stay then they would be considered willing.
But otherwise right they are considered, you know, otherwise they're considered to
be doing it out of יראה. yira. You know this is very
interesting, it plays out like the רמב"ם Rambam discusses in his אגרת
השמד Iggeret HaShmad about people that were under the threat of like,
you know, that they had to convert out of, you know, to
Islam because or else risk being executed or whatever. And the רמב"ם
Rambam talks about like, you
know, what if you were to publicly you know observe your Judaism,
but he says but that's as long as you don't have an
opportunity to leave that you could be considered אנוס Anus while you're
there. As soon as you have an opportunity to leave and you're
not leaving, then he says then you can't be considered an אנוס
Anus anymore. So you know it's an interesting parallel to this thing,
like there's one thing to be seemingly doing things willingly, like what
does it mean to be forced? You don't always have to have
a gun to your head, like if you're not doing this, you
know you're doing it because of your sense of the overall threat
and the consequences of what it would mean to do otherwise. Okay,
but once you actually have an opportunity to leave, that's different. So
this is very relevant to this issue, right? So there's really all
like a range of scenarios about אונס, Oness, right? There's the אונס
Oness about literally you know physically at that moment being forced and
raped and so on. There's being in a context in which you
know you might act willingly, you know you might willingly have sex
with the guy or you know do all these various things, but
it's because if you're not going to do that, you're afraid what's
that the consequences, you're afraid for your life. And that actually is
also considered אונס. Oness. Okay, so that all makes a lot of
sense. The question then is when does it begin to become רצון?
Ratzon? And there also we have two different like types of scenarios.
We have the case about like you know being raped and in
the middle of the act sort of saying oh no I want
it where at least we'll put aside אבוה דשמואל, Avo De'Shmuel, at
least you know at least רבא Rava says that that case is
not considered real רצון, Ratzon, right? Because it's a resulting from even
if you're sincere, even if the woman is sincere, maybe it's resulting
from you know somehow the initial again it's hard for us to
imagine how that initial act could lead to רצון, Ratzon, but anyway
but we'll frame it that way. And then I think the more
interesting question is the one that David raised which isn't directly addressed
here which is sort of the mirror image of this case of
אונס, Oness, which is is that if a person maybe you know
or not mirror anyway a person is given an opportunity, maybe it
is this case, a person is given an opportunity to leave and
they wind up staying, but maybe nevertheless it's all ultimately can be
seen as how they've been influenced and resulting from the original thing.
This last case seems to say against that. This last case seems
to say once they're given the opportunity to leave and they don't
leave we can no longer frame it as אונס. Oness. Okay, but
so now we can the גמרא Gemara continues, wraps this up. The
גמרא Gemara says like this. תנו
רבנן
Tanu
Rabbanan שבוי מלכות הרי הן כשבויין. Shvuyey Malchut Harey Hen Kishvuyin. So
ones that are taken captive by the king are considered like captives
and presumably for having sex with it really means by like the
government, but as we'll see in a minute the גמרא Gemara is
going to sound like it means by the king for the purpose
of having sex with the king then that's considered to be to
be captives and it's an אונס Oness and the women can go
back to their to their to their to their husbands. גנובי ליסטות
אינם כשבויין. Ginuvey Listos Einam Kishvuyin. But those taken
by captors are not like שבויים Shvuyin and they cannot go back
to their husbands. So the גמרא Gemara says ותניא איפכא? Vatanya Ipcha?
Don't we don't we but we have a ברייתא Baraita says the
exact
opposite? מלכות אמלכות לא קשיא. Malchut Amalchut Lo Kashya. No it's not
difficult. הא במלכות אחשורוש הא במלכות בן נצר. Ha Bemalchut Achashverosh Ha
Bemalchut Ben Nezar. So if it's the king is אחשורוש, Achashverosh, then
רש״י Rashi says you know that I unless you're אסתר Esther the
king is never going to marry you, never going to take you
for a wife. So therefore you're never really a willing participant okay
and therefore you're it's always considered raped. If however the guy is
this guy בן נצר Ben Nezar who was apparently some bandit but
also he was a bandit that was actually seizing a lot of
territory and sort of starting up his own little government, okay he
was like the I guess the ISIS of the past or something.
Anyway and there you think that it maybe if I am a
willing participant maybe he'll actually marry me and maybe I'll get to
be his queen because you don't need to be of royal blood
because this guy's a commoner. Okay, so there we're afraid that even
if the woman is seized by for sex by the by the
leader that maybe she'll be willing because maybe she wants to be
queen. Okay, so that's the context, that's why one says מלכות Malchut
is a problem and one says it isn't. ליסטות אליסטות לא קשיא
Listos Alistos Lo Kashya and the contradiction of the cases of bandits
is not a difficulty. הא בבן נצר Ha BeBen Nezar the other
ברייתא Baraita considers ליסטות Listos to be referring because בן נצר Ben
Nezar was both a bandit and a king as it were. He's
a bandit king. So there you go. So when it says that
it that it is a that a taken by a bandit we
consider the woman to have been willing, that was the case of
בן נצר Ben Nezar because maybe she wanted to do it because
she wanted to be queen. הא בליסטין דעלמא Ha Belistin De'alma normal
bandits we assume that she's not willing because why should she be
willing and we'll assume it's rape. ובן נצר U'Ben Nezar so how
do you deal with בן נצר? Ben Nezar? התם קרי ליה מלכא
הכא קרי ליה ליסטים. Hasam Kari Ley Malka Hacha Kari Ley Listim.
In one ברייתא Baraita he's called the king, in another ברייתא Baraita
he's called the bandit. אין גבי אחשורוש ליסטים In Gabei Achashverosh Listim
compared to אחשורוש Achashverosh who's really of royal blood he's a bandit,
הא וגבי ליסטים דעלמא מלכא הוי Hu Vegabei Listim De'alma Malka Havey
but by other bandits he's a king. So there you go. It's
like that old joke you know the joke about the guy makes
a million dollars and he buys himself a yacht and he gets
you know he dresses up in his like sailor suit with the
you know brass buttons or whatever and he goes and shows has
little sailor hat and he shows his mom he gives her like
a tour of the
yacht. So alright, anyway, moving on.
So what we have here is a really, like I said, a
very on the one hand deeply disturbing גמרא Gemara in terms of
thinking that this woman in the middle of an act of rape
can be willingly participating, but at the other hand an interesting גמרא
Gemara in terms of framing what's considered אונס. onus. And at the
end of the day, the גמרא Gemara is, let's just appreciate that
at the end of the day, the גמרא Gemara is pretty broad
in defining אונס. onus. אונס onus is even if in the middle
of the act she says, "No, actually I want it," and even
if we think she's being sincere about saying she wants it, if
you could imagine such a case, we still say it resulted from
the original אונס. onus. And even
if they're being held captive over a long period of time and
they seem to be willing, nevertheless we say it's
אונס onus because of the fear of what will happen if they
don't act in a willing way. But the only way we won't
consider it אונס onus is if they're given an option to leave
and then they don't leave.
Okay, so that's in terms of אשת ישראל. Eishet Yisrael. Now we
get to the כהנת, Kohenet, okay? And the גמרא Gemara here is
not focusing on the general issue, which is also of course challenging
about the way that חז"ל Chazal understand that the category in the
תורה Torah of a זונה zonah is not a woman who literally
is a prostitute but any woman who's had sex with a man
that she's not able to
marry, and whether it's willing or unwilling, the idea that we understand
that the category of זונה zonah applies even in the case of
unwilling sex and that that makes this woman who is raped forbidden
to her husband that's the כהן. Kohen. So the גמרא Gemara brackets
that, that's taken for granted and now we take a look at
the כתובה Ketubah aspects of this.
ובכהנת הדרינא למדינתך. u've'Kohenet adrina l'medinateich. And for a כהנת Kohenet he
says, "I will return you to your country," but I'm not returning
you as a wife because I won't be able to stay married
to you. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: אלמנה לכהן גדול חייב לפדותה. almana
l'Kohen Gadol chayav liftosa. Let's say a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol married
an אלמנה, almana, okay? Or you could say a כהן Kohen married
a גרושה, gerusha, anyway he has to redeem her.
שאני קורא בה she'ani korei bah because the line in the כתובה
Ketubah applies to her, ובכהנת הדרינא למדינתך. u've'Kohenet adrina l'medinateich. He says,
"I will return you to your country," so therefore he still has
those obligations because those obligations apply even if she is not allowed
to remain his wife. So even this woman who
began as his wife but it was legally not allowed to be
his wife, nevertheless those obligations still obtain. Now what I have to
explain is the following. Surprisingly, I think you all remember from whatever
things we've done in the past, that קידושין kiddushin by איסורי לאוין
issurei lavin is binding. If a כהן Kohen marries a גרושה, gerusha,
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol marries an אלמנה, almana, ישראל Yisrael marries a
ממזרת, mamzeret, the קידושין kiddushin is still binding, they're married and you
need a גט get and if the woman were to commit adultery
it would be adultery. Not only that, what you might be really
surprised to find out is that the כתובה Ketubah obligations even exist.
Now you might have said, why are the rabbis imposing the כתובה
Ketubah obligations if they basically would want this couple to get divorced?
So the כתובה Ketubah obligations which exist are the ones which are
not about their ongoing marital status. So for example, the lump sum
payment she gets at divorce, that exists because why should she be
out the money to protect her and she still needs that. Of
course you could argue the opposite, you could argue that that money
is in order that he shouldn't casually divorce her, that was one
of the reasons for that lump sum payment. But nevertheless, it's a
payment that's made not as part of their ongoing marriage, it's a
payment that's made once they're divorced, so she still gets that. Okay,
however she does not get for example
food
and רפואה refuah and all those types of things are the types
of ongoing financial obligations that is part of them remaining married and
we want to encourage them to get divorced so we want to
basically say you don't get any of those ongoing payments and therefore
it's not in your financial interest to remain married and therefore that
hopefully will encourage divorce. Of course, funny thing is that makes it
easier for the husband, he doesn't have to pay any money so
in a way he's the one we gotta encourage to get divorced,
not her. Anyway, we don't want to maintain those כתובה Ketubah obligations
that are about
their ongoing marital relationship. Okay,
so what about the obligation to redeem her? So that actually is
not about sustaining the ongoing marriage. Because for a כהן, Kohen, the
obligation to redeem her is actually and then he's going to redeem
her and then they're going to get divorced, because a כהן Kohen
he can't remain married to her anyway. So that's what the statement
here is that if basically it was an illicit marriage but it
was still binding, אלמנה לכהן גדול, almana l'Kohen Gadol, and it was
about a כהן, Kohen, then he does have the obligation to redeem
her because that's not an obligation that is in the context of
them remaining married. However, if you look at the next line it'll
help clarify it, top finally we get to today's דף, daf, ממזרת
ונתינה לישראל אינו חייב לפדותה. mamzeret u'netinah l'Israel eino chayav liftosa. If
however it was a ישראל Israel who married a ממזרת... mamzeret... or
anything, he does not have to redeem her. Why? כי אין אני
קורא בו והשיבותיך לי לאינתו, Ki ein ani korei bo v'hashivotecha li
l'into, because then the line 'I will return you as my wife'
doesn't apply. So I mean what the גמרא Gemara has explicitly said
here is that whether the line of the כתובה Ketubah applies in
this case or not, what I'm telling you and which is based
on what רש"י Rashi says, what רש"י Rashi clarifies is it's also
that we will not, we will not, you know, maintain the כתובה
Ketubah obligations, we will not uphold the כתובה Ketubah obligations if they
are in the context of them remaining married in this type of
a case where the marriage is forbidden.
Meaning if you're under the same roof at that point?
No, meaning if the nature of the obligation reflects the idea that
they're going to remain husband and wife.
Even if they're under the same?
Even if they're under the same roof. So if the case by
the כהנת kohenet and the, what do you call it, the אלמנה
לכהן גדול almanah l'Kohen Gadol or גרושה לכהן, gerushah l'kohen, since after
redeeming they're not supposed to remain married, so the obligation to redeem
still applies. Whereas by a כהן kohen and a ממזר, mamzer, since
the nature obligation of redeeming, the normal obligation of redeeming is and
then you remain married, so in this case where they're not supposed
to remain married, the obligation of redeeming does not apply.
ומדינה U'medinah here means country and not city?
Probably city, yeah, you're right. Okay, שאיני קורא בו והשיבותיך לי לאינתו.
she'eini korei bo v'hashivotecha li l'into. רבא אמר כל שאיסור שבויה גורם
לה חייב לפדותה איסור דבר אחר גורם לה אינו חייב לפדותה.
Rava amar kol she'issur shevuyah goreim lah chayav lifdosah, issur davar
acheir goreim lah eino chayav lifdosah. רבא Rava says no, when the
כתובה Ketubah says 'I'll return you to your country, to your city',
meaning even though you won't remain my wife, that only means if
you won't remain my wife as a result of what do you
call it, as a result of the fact that you were taken
captive. Meaning I still will have an obligation to redeem you even
though you were taken captive and even though as a result of
that I won't be able to keep you as my wife. But
if I'm not able to keep you as my wife for another
reason, like you're an אלמנה almanah or you were a גרושה gerushah
etc., then in that case I don't have any obligation to redeem
you. Okay, so the fact that the language of the כתובה Ketubah
suggests that the obligation to redeem applies even if they can't remain
husband and wife, רבא Rava says it's only if they can't remain
husband and wife as a result of her being taken as a
שבויה. shevuyah. But if there's another reason that they shouldn't have been
husband and wife to begin with because it was an אלמנה almanah
or it was a גרושה gerushah or whatever it might have been,
then that obligation doesn't apply because that obligation is fundamentally an obligation
between husband and wife and they shouldn't have been husband and wife
to begin with. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לימא כתנאי, Leima
k'tana'ei, let's say that this is linked to a debate of תנאים
Tanna'im because we taught the following. המדיר את אשתו ונשבית. Hamadir es
ishto v'nishbeys. A person makes a vow that his wife can't get
any benefit from him. Now, if he takes the vow that his
wife can't get any benefit from him, he has to divorce his
wife because you can't live together as husband and wife with such
a vow. Okay, so this basically just sets up a scenario where
he is obligated to divorce her. So they're already in a scenario
where they're obligated to get divorced and then she gets taken
captive. רבי אליעזר אומר פודה ונותן לה כתובתה. Rabbi Eliezer omer podeh
v'nosein lah kesuvashah. You have to redeem her because that's your כתובה
Ketubah obligation and then you have to divorce her and give her
the כתובה Ketubah. because you guys have to get divorced. רבי יהושע
אומר נותן לה כתובתה ואינה פודה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer nosein lah kesuvashah
v'einah podeh. No, you pay out her כתובה Ketubah because you have
to get divorced but you don't have to redeem her. אמר רבי
נתן שאלתי את סומכוס. Amar Rabbi Natan sha'alti es Sumchos. I asked
סומכוס, Sumchos, who is a student of
רבי מאיר, 'when רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said נותן לה כתובתה ואינה
פודה, nosein lah kesuvashah v'einah podeh, that you can just pay out
her כתובה Ketubah and you don't have to redeem her? Right, you
divorce her but you don't redeem her. כשהדירה ולבסוף נשבית? Keshedirah ul'vasof
nishbeys? Would this be only if the vow preceded her being taken
captive? Because then they were already in a state where they had
to get divorced when she was taken captive. או נשבית ולבסוף הדירה?
O nishbeys ul'vasof pedirah? Would it be even if she was first
taken captive and then he made a vow?' ואמר לי, V'amar li,
and he said to me, לא שמעתי. Lo shamati. 'You know what,
I didn't hear explicitly, ונראין הדברים, v'nir'in hadevarim, but it seems כשהדירה
ולבסוף נשבית, keshedirah ul'vasof nishbeys, that he would only have an obligation
if first he made a vow and they were obligated to get
divorced and then she was taken captive. So when she was taken
captive, they were already, you know, getting divorced, as it were. So
therefore his obligation to redeem her
didn't apply. דאי אמרת, D'ee amart, because now the גמרא Gemara adds
in, you could tell by the shift to Aramaic, because were you
to say נשבית ולבסוף הדירה, nishbeys ul'vasof pedirah, that if she was
taken captive and then he took a vow and then he would
have to redeem her because then אתי לאערומי, asi l'arumey, he's going
to, you know, scheme. Right, here's a great way of getting out
of having to redeem your wife. You know, she's taken captive, they're
asking $100,000, that's a כתובה ketubah obligation, but the actual כתובה ketubah
itself, the lump sum payment of the כתובה ketubah is 10,000. So
why don't I do this? Why don't I take a vow, now
we're obligated to get divorced and now I don't have to redeem
her and now I'll just pay out her כתובה. So obviously it
would only be that the vow preceded. Okay, but what do you
see from this? You see that there's a debate in a case
of a husband and wife that have to get divorced. Is there
a כתובה obligation or not a כתובה obligation? Right, that's the question.
I mean, is there an obligation to redeem or not an obligation
to redeem when a husband and wife have to get divorced? So
maybe this parallels this whole discussion. So the גמרא says מאי לאו.
mai lav. Are we not talking about במדיר אשתו קמיפלגי bemadir ishto
kamiflagi
that we're talking about, the only reason that you might have an
obligation since you have how could you since you have to get
divorced is that it's the wife of a כהן? Cohen? אביי אמר
כרבי אליעזר ורבא אמר כרבי יהושע. Abaye amar k'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rava amar
k'Rabbi Yehoshua. And אביי Abaye says like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבא Rava says like רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, which means the following.
And we'll end with this now. But if we're talking about not
the wife of a כהן, Cohen, the גמרא at this stage imagines
that of course you would not have to redeem her because the
כתובה by a non-wife of a כהן Cohen says I'll redeem you
to me as a wife, I'll bring you back to me as
a wife, and since they went since they were taken captive they
were in the process of getting divorced and they had to get
divorced, it's not possible to say I'll bring you back as a
wife. So it assumes that if it was the wife of a
כהן, Cohen, nobody would say it. This case would be as the
wife of a ישראל. Yisrael. This case is a wife of a
כהן. Cohen.
And therefore it's a wife of a כהן, Cohen, so even though
they had to get divorced, the כתובה still says I'll redeem you
even though we won't stay married, I'll redeem you and bring you
back to your city. And that seems to be the debate. In
a case where some other thing other than her captivity is preventing
them from staying married, by the case of a wife of a
כהן, Cohen, are you still obligated is he going to still be
obligated to redeem her or not? Okay, the language of the כתובה
says does say I'll bring you back, not that you'll be my
wife. So maybe the obligation would still exist. Or maybe it would
say since before the captivity they were obligated to get divorced, then
fundamentally the obligation to redeem does not exist. Okay, so we'll continue
with this tomorrow. All
right, I have no idea how we are going to catch up
and
oh that is true, it's a longer שבת. Shabbat.
Yeah, it's like שבת הגדול, Shabbat HaGadol, we can do it after
מנחה.
Mincha. Are we going to have the